{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "A duchy of this name was ruled by a monarch nicknamed “Longsword” and founded by his father, Rollo. A woman named Emma hailed from this region and married Ethelred the Unready. A duke of this region wed Matilda of Flanders and launched an invasion that culminated in the 1066 Battle of Hastings and conquest of Anglo-Saxon England. For ten points, name this region of north France, the home of William the Conqueror.",
      "answer": "Normandy"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 2006, an athlete in this sport professed the “whiskey defense” to explain his positive urine test, which was made public four days after he beat Oscar Pereiro to win this sport’s premiere event. Another athlete in this sport founded the Livestrong Foundation after surviving testicular cancer and won this sport’s annual three-week-long race through Western Europe seven times. Floyd Landis and Lance Armstrong disgraced, for ten points, what sport’s Tour de France road race?",
      "answer": [
        "bicycle racing",
        "word forms"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Mount Fortress was built to protect members of this religion. Fumi-e were pictures that members of this religion stepped on to prove innocence. Twenty-six members of this religion were executed after their protection was revoked by the Shimazu clan. “Hidden” members of this religion revolted in the Shimabara Rebellion. This religion was banned by sakoku law in Japan. For ten points, name this religion that was spread to Qing China by Jesuit missionaries.",
      "answer": "Roman Catholicism"
    },
    {
      "question": "At one battle in this location, General Hemu lost his eye to an arrow, leading to his defeat by Bairam Khan and a 13-year old Akbar. Ahmad Shah and the Durrani Empire won a later battle at this location. Another victory at this site led to the fall of the Dehli Sultanate under Ibrahim Lodi and the rise of Babur. For ten points, name this location of three prominent battles, in 1526, 1556, and 1761 in India, the first of which established the Mughal Empire.",
      "answer": "Battles of Panipat"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader argued that “the prospect of domination of the nation’s scholars by Federal employment [...] is gravely to be regarded.” This man delivered a “message of leave-taking and farewell” that explained “Americanmakersofplowsharescould[...]makeswordsaswell”andwarnedagainstthemilitary-industrial complex. For ten points, name this 20th century President whose advice regarding the defense industry derived from his service as Allied Commander in World War II.",
      "answer": "Dwight D. Eisenhower"
    },
    {
      "question": "A Syrian holder of this position took it at age 14, was plagued by numerous sex scandals, and was assassinated at age 18. In addition to Elagabalus, an earlier holder of this position mocked legislators by suggesting his horse Incitatus could serve as consul; that man was nicknamed “little boots” and was assassinated by the Praetorian Guard. For ten points, name this position held by madmen like Caligula.",
      "answer": "Emperor of Rome"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man met his business partner, Phineas Miller, while staying at the Mulberry Grove estate of Revolutionary War widow Catherine Greene. He received a government contract to produce ten thousand muskets in two years, during which he pioneered the use of replaceable parts in gun manufacturing. This man developed a machine that used a wire mesh to isolate seeds from the fibers of a crop widely grown in the American south. For ten points, name this inventor of the cotton gin.",
      "answer": "Eli Whitney"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these objects includes an unusually gory depiction of Jesus in the center, was thought to have healing powers, and was created for a hospital for lepers in Isenheim. Another one of these artworks includes a panel showing the Adoration of the Mystic Lamb and a triple-crowned Almighty figure; that example was created by the van Eyck brothers. For ten points, name these religious artworks created for the center of churches, including one in Ghent.",
      "answer": [
        "altarpieces",
        "descriptions like “paintings placed behind an altar”"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This political faction was opposed by the White League and the Red Shirts, paramilitary groups that supported the Redeemers. This faction passed legislation that created five districts, each ruled by a different general. Anticipating the dismissal of War Secretary Edwin Stanton, this faction passed the Tenure of Office Act. Thaddeus Stevens led, for ten points, what Reconstruction-era political faction that tried to impeach Andrew Johnson?",
      "answer": "Radical Republicans"
    },
    {
      "question": "This body of water, also known as Lago Cochibola, contains a namesake population of freshwater sharks. The first registered Spanish settlement in mainland North America, Granada, is on its shores. The Bryan-Chamorro Treaty gave the US rights to build a canal through this lake, a proposal recently revived by an Hong Kong consortium. For ten points, name this largest lake in Central America, connected by the Tipitapa River to Lake Managua, found in a country also home to the Contras and Sandinistas.",
      "answer": "Lake Nicaragua"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This government was served by Nathalie Lemel’s Women’s Union. Members of this government destroyed the Vendˆome Column on the orders of the artist Gustave Courbet [core-bay]. Adolphe Thiers [tee-air] ordered Marshal MacMahon to violently end this government during the Bloody Week. Karl Marx argued that this government was an example of the dictatorship of the proletariat. For ten points, name this socialist government that, after the loss of the Franco-Prussian War, briefly ruled from the French capital.",
        "answer": "Paris Commune"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This palace, the home of French monarchs after 1564, was also destroyed during the Paris Commune. It shares its name with a garden in Paris adjacent to the Louvre.",
        "answer": "Tuileries Palace or Garden"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This theory utilizes a coordinate system on a four-dimensional manifold named for Hermann Minkowski. Motivation for this theory was provided by the Michelson-Morley and Trouton-Noble experiments suggesting the non-existence of luminiferous aether. This theory introduced the notion of mass-energy equivalence and assumes nothing can travel faster than the speed of light. For ten points, name this theory proposed by Albert Einstein in 1905, ten years before a similar “General” theory.",
        "answer": "special relativity"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The group of spacetime isometries used in special relativity is named for this French mathematician, who also names a topological conjecture that was proved by Perelman in 2003.",
        "answer": [
          "Henri Poincare",
          "Poincare conjecture",
          "theorem"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this state, Charles Brooks was killed by lethal injection, the first such execution in the world. In 1998 in this state, three white supremacists killed James Byrd, Jr. by dragging him behind a truck through Jasper. One of Byrd’s murderers refused to eat a lavish last meal, after which this state ended its practice of completing special requests for the condemned. For ten points, name this state that, since 1976, has carried out more than one-third of American criminal executions, including under Governors Rick Perry and George W. Bush.",
        "answer": "Texas"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A 2009 expansion of federal hate crime legislation was named for the aforementioned James Byrd and Matthew Shepard; in 1998, Shepard was tortured and left to die in this state’s town of Laramie.",
        "answer": "Wyoming"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city joined a conflict when its rival attempted to besiege Potidaea, violating the Thirty Years’ Peace. Under Lysander, this city’s fleet successfully set up an ambush at Aegospotami; this city’s fleet had also aided Syracuse against the Sicilian Expedition, launched by the Delian League. In 404 BC, this city overthrew democratic rule in their vanquished enemy after winning the Peloponnesian War. For ten points, name this ancient Greek city-state whose well-trained army subjugated Athens.",
        "answer": "Sparta or Lacedaemon"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Sparta replaced Athenian democracy with this numbered group of oligarchs, led by Critias. They ruled for a little over a year, exiled or killed thousands of Athenians, and were overthrown in the Phyle campaign.",
        "answer": "Thirty Tyrants"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer’s second symphony was written to celebrate the 400th anniversary of Gutenberg’s invention of the printing press, and he included a Martin Luther hymn in the finale of his fifth symphony. ThiscomposerofLobgesang andtheReformation Symphoniesincludedasaltarelloinhisfourthsymphony, nicknamed Italian. For ten points, name this German composer who wrote several Venetian boat songs for his Songs Without Words and wrote incidental music for Shakespeare’s A Midsummer Night’s Dream.",
        "answer": "Felix Mendelssohn-Bartholdy"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mendelssohn wrote the soprano part in Elijah for this singer, who toured America under the management of P.T. Barnum and was nicknamed the “Swedish Nightingale.”",
        "answer": "Jenny Lind"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After it was revealed that this country’s former president gave money to Paul Manafort, Manafort was dismissed as manager of the Trump presidential campaign. This country’s president is known as the “Chocolate King” since he controls the chocolate manufacturing group Roshen. The Minsk II agreement was signed in an attempt to de-escalate the war in the Donbass Region of this country. The Euromaidan protests led to the ousting of this country’s president, Viktor Yanukovych. For ten points, name this country led by Petro Poroshenko whose Crimean Peninsula was annexed by Russia in 2014.",
        "answer": "Ukraine"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The two separatist groups in eastern Ukraine are based around the Donetsk Oblast and this city’s oblast. The Merheleva Ridge is a prehistoric burial complex found in 2006 in its namesake oblast.",
        "answer": "Luhansk or Lugansk"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1835, this man replaced a scheduled speaker, George Thompson, who canceled due to a $100 reward for the first person to injure him; this man was then nearly lynched. This man convinced Wendell Philips to give up his law practice in favor of focusing on his social movement, which this man advocated for in a Quaker newspaper, Genius of Universal Emancipation. The American Anti-Slavery Society was founded by, for ten points, what abolitionist and publisher of The Liberator?",
        "answer": "William Lloyd Garrison"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Garrison very briefly supported this general concept, for which the ACS advocated. The city of Monrovia was founded by supporters of, and participants in, this process. Description acceptable.",
        "answer": "repatriation movement"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Description acceptable. An attempt at this action in Smolensk involved plastic explosives disguised as two bottles of brandy. The Reserve Army was activated after one attempt of this action, though its commander, Friedrich Fromm, turned on former ally Friedrich Olbricht. A bomb set off at the Wolf’s Lair nearly performed this action. Claus von Stauffenberg’s Operation Valkyrie called for, for ten points, what action that would have decapitated the Third Reich?",
        "answer": [
          "assassinating Adolf Hitler",
          "equivalents",
          "Operation Valkyrie",
          "the July 20 plot after “Reserve Army” is said"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the aftermath of Valkyrie, impromptu executions of culprits were stopped by the arrival of SS troops under this man, the leader of Operation Greif. The previous year, this commando personally rescued Benito Mussolini during the glider raid on Gran Sasso.",
        "answer": "Otto Skorzeny"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Supreme Court Justices",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Current Chief Justice.",
          "answer": "John Roberts"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Chief Justice.",
          "answer": "John Jay"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Latina justice, appointed by Barack Obama in 2009.",
          "answer": "Sonia Sotomayor"
        },
        {
          "question": "First female justice, appointed by Ronald Reagan.",
          "answer": "Sandra Day O’Connor"
        },
        {
          "question": "First African-American justice, appointed in 1967.",
          "answer": "Thurgood Marshall"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Jewish justice, appointed in 1916.",
          "answer": "Louis Brandeis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Only Justice to dissent in Plessy v. Ferguson.",
          "answer": "John Marshall Harlan I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who resigned as Associate Justice to run for President in 1916; he lost.",
          "answer": "Charles Evans Hughes"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Assassination of Franz Ferdinand",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Global war it sparked.",
          "answer": [
            "World War I or the Great War",
            "the War to End All Wars"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Twenty-year-old Serbian assassin.",
          "answer": "Gavrilo Princip"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern-day Bosnian city in which it took place.",
          "answer": "Sarajevo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Colorfully named Serbian secret society that organized the attack.",
          "answer": [
            "Black Hand",
            "Unification",
            "Death"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country from which Franz Ferdinand was heir apparent, and which controlled the Serbian territory.",
          "answer": "Austria-Hungary"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wife of Franz Ferdinand who was also killed in the attack.",
          "answer": [
            "Sophie von Chotkow, Duchess of Hohenberg",
            "either underlined portion"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Poison that failed to kill bomber Nedejlko Cabrinovic [neh-dyell-koh cah-brin-oh-vitch] after he jumped into a shallow river.",
          "answer": "cyanide pill"
        },
        {
          "question": "Serbian teacher who recruited the assassins and was hanged in 1915.",
          "answer": "Danilo Ili´c"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Mexican Revolution",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "European country that sent the Zimmermann Telegram to Mexico during the revolution, trying to trigger an invasion of the US.",
          "answer": "Germany"
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. president who intervened by occupying Veracruz and led the US during World War I.",
          "answer": "Woodrow Wilson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Artist of Man at the Crossroads who supported the revolution with his murals.",
          "answer": "Diego Rivera"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political party founded after the Revolution, which dominated Mexican politics for much of the 20th century.",
          "answer": [
            "PRI or Partido Revolucionario Institucional",
            "Institutional Revolutionary Party"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolutionary who led a peasant revolution in Morelos, authored the Plan of Ayala, and inspired an agrarian movement.",
          "answer": [
            "Emiliano Zapata",
            "Zapatistas"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Longtime dictator of Mexico overthrown during the revolution.",
          "answer": "Porfirio D´ıaz"
        },
        {
          "question": "The man who led the initial revolution with the Plan of San Luis Potos´ı. He became president after the Treaty of Ciudad Ju´arez.",
          "answer": "Francisco Madero"
        },
        {
          "question": "General that launched the Ten Tragic Days coup to become President of Mexico.",
          "answer": "Victoriano Huerta"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In Beijing in April 2013, this non-Asian country’s leader insisted he would send troops to back a hypothetical US invasion of North Korea. This country’s recently-resigned Prime Minister, John Key, had been elected in 2008 over long time Labour leader (20 pts)",
        "Helen Clark. Kyle Lockwood designed the proposed “Silver Fern” flag for this country, an option in a failed March 2016 referendum to replace this country’s current flag, which features the (10 pts)",
        "Union Jack and Southern Cross. For ten points, name this country in Oceania whose cities include Wellington and Auckland."
      ],
      "answer": "New Zealand"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This civilization produced the Linen Book of Zagreb, the only surviving book made of linen, as well as the Sarcophagus of the Spouses. This civilization’s language was long considered to be an (20 pts)",
        "isolate and uses large clusters of consonants due to a stress on the initial syllable. A loss at the Battle of Veii signaled the fall of this civilization, which referred to themselves as the Rasena. (10 pts)",
        "Lars Porsena was a leader of, for ten points, what northern Italian civilization that was led by Tarquin the Proud before it was assimilated into Rome?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Etruscans",
        "Rasenna before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was accused of working with John van Vossen and Robert Rose in aiding the Cherokees, a charge that prompted him to beat accuser William Stanberry with a cane. He was replaced by (20 pts)",
        "Mirabeau Lamar in his highest post after he refused to lend support to the Confederacy. During a revolution against (10 pts)",
        "Mexican rule, this man masterminded a victory over Santa Anna at San Jacinto. For ten points, name this first president of the Texan Republic, honored as the namesake of Texas’ most populous city."
      ],
      "answer": "Sam Houston"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The restoration of a modern version of this school of thought was supported by the “Criticize Lin” campaign. The “Two Handles” are emphasized in this school of thought as ways to control the citizenry. (20 pts)",
        "Shang Yang, a philosopher in this school of thought, was responsible for its implementation during the Warring States Period. The most famous proponent of this school of thought ruled the state of (10 pts)",
        "Qin. For ten points, name this ancient Chinese school of political thought focusing on the enforcement of law, notably opposed to Confucianism."
      ],
      "answer": "Legalism"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This event was the subject of a painting by Karl Briullov that became the basis for a novel by Edward Bulwer-Lytton. This event was discussed in a letter written from Misenum and addressed to (20 pts)",
        "Tacitus. This event preserved writings like “Gaius Pumidius Diphilus was here,” which had been written as early graffiti. (10 pts)",
        "Pliny the Elder died during this event, which buried Herculaneum in a pyroclastic flow. For ten points, name this event in 79 AD that destroyed the Roman city of Pompeii."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "eruption of Mt. Vesuvius",
        "elaborations",
        "descriptions of “the destruction of Pompeii until “Herculaneum” is read, then"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Pope Innocent X called this agreement “null, void...and empty of meaning and effect for all time” in Zelo Domus Dei. This treaty led Spain to acknowledge the independence of the (20 pts)",
        "Dutch Republic and to officially recognize the Treaty of Augsburg’s principle of “cuius regio, eius religio.” This treaty created a namesake system of coexisting sovereign states and was signed at (10 pts)",
        "Osnabruck and Munster. For ten points, name this treaty that ended the Thirty Years’ War."
      ],
      "answer": "Peace of Westphalia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An abandoned proposal to dam this river near Tocks Island led to the creation of a “water gap” National Recreation Area. Tributaries of this river, whose valley was home to the colony of New Sweden, include the Christina and the (20 pts)",
        "Schuylkill [skool-kul]. Ice on this river was a major obstacle to carrying out a successful attack on Johann Rall’s (10 pts)",
        "Hessians, who were quartered along its banks in Trenton during the American Revolution. For ten points, name this river which was crossed on the night of Christmas, December 1776 by George Washington."
      ],
      "answer": "Delaware River"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This party split into two separate factions after 1956 when its final presidential candidate, Darlington Hoopes, won fewer than 6,000 votes. Walter Lippmann founded the National Party to (20 pts)",
        "oppose this party after World War I. Assisting the ARU during the Pullman strike got a candidate from this political party (10 pts)",
        "imprisoned; that same member was later arrested under the Espionage Act of 1917. For ten points, name this American political party, sponsored by progressives and labor unions, for which Eugene Debs ran for President five times."
      ],
      "answer": "Socialist Party of America"
    }
  ]
}